Sai Preetham Dongari

dongarisaipreetham@gmail.com | Ph: (774)-828-0664 | LinkedIn | Greater Boston Area, USA (Ready to Relocate)

Summary

Over 2.5 years of experience as a skilled software engineer with expertise in SDLC, specializing in front-end and back-end development with strong proficiency in JavaScript, React.js, Node.js, SQL, Python, and AWS. My strengths are complemented by strong problem-solving skills, attention to detail, and a passion for staying updated with the latest technologies and best practices.

Education

Masters in Computer Science, Clark University | Worcester, MA | GPA: 3.74

May 2024

Excelled as a Teaching Assistant for three consecutive semesters, providing outstanding mentorship and instructional support

B.Tech. in Information Technology, Sreenidhi Institute of Science & Technology | Hyderabad, INDIA | GPA: 8.0Gold Reward for Missing child Identification project. [International Innovation Show E-NNOVATE Oct 2021]

July 2021

Experience

Teaching Assistant

Clark University

January 2023 - May 2024 | Worcester, MA

- Facilitated hands-on lab sessions for **200+** students, guided them in selecting research topics, and provided feedback on assignments, enhancing their understanding of **Software Engineering** and **Securing the blockchain**.
- Converted and integrated **10000+** rows of CLARKCOUGARS basketball data (1992-2023) into **SQL**, dynamically fetching real-time data using **React Axios**, resulting in significant cost savings for the university by replacing proprietary software.
- Developed a research management app under Prof. Gio using ReactJS, Express JS, NodeJS, and MongoDB, streamlining research papers.

Software Engineer

Tata Consultancy Services

August 2021 - July 2022 | Hyderabad, India

- Developed web components and RESTful web services using technologies like **Spring boot**, **MySQL**, **Sitecore**, **HTML**, **CSS** and **Angular**. Troubleshooted and resolved multiple bugs within existing features.
- Implemented Angular services to connect the web application to back-end APIs to POST/GET the data used in the application.
- Worked closely with **UI/UX** designers to implement responsive designs and ensure consistency with design mock-ups, while collaborating with other teams to fix user interface defects.

Software Engineer

Urban Rebox IT PVT

January 2020 - June 2021 | Hyderabad, India

- Developed and maintained a responsive frontend for Urban Rebox IT's waste management app using **HTML5**, **CSS3**, and **JavaScript**, reducing user complaints and improving engagement for **4000+** users.
- Engaged in DevOps processes, using Jenkins for continuous integration and deployment.
- Took part in designing and optimizing MySQL databases, writing SQL queries and basic stored procedures for real-time data processing, ensuring seamless data flow and improving system efficiency.

Skills

C, Python, SQL, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, React.js, Node.js, Express.js, Django, Redux, Angular, MongoDB, AWS S3, AWS RDS, Restful API's, JWT, OAuth, Git, Postman, Jest

Projects

Chat with PDF | Intelligent Document Interaction Platform

January 2024-May 2024

- Developed and deployed "Chat with PDF" using React.js, Tailwind CSS, Node.js, Express.js, AWS S3, and Pinecone, integrating OpenAI NLP models to reduce search time by 50% and increase accuracy by 30%.
- Developed backend APIs with **Node.js** and **Express.js**, integrating **AWS S3** and Pinecone for secure, fast semantic searches, achieving a 30% accuracy increase with custom algorithms and real-time query processing.

EcomEase | E-commerce Platform with Admin Panel and Payment Integration

August 2023-Dec 2023

- Created an e-commerce application with a React JS frontend and an admin dashboard using Express and Node for a seamless shopping.
- Integrated **Redux** Toolkit with Async Thunk and React Router v6 for efficient state management and navigation, established a secure backend server with MongoDB, Express, and Passport JS, and deployed on **Vercel** with Stripe for payments and **Nodemailer** for emails.

FlashHire | Web Application for Employment Opportunities

January 2023-May 2023

- Developed a full-stack web application with a team of two using Java Spring Boot, JPA, **Hibernate**, **MySQL** on **AWS RDS**, **React**, **Tailwind** CSS, and Redux, enhancing job matching by 30% and reducing response times by 25%.
- Architected a secure multi-role user authentication framework with JWT and Spring Security, and built an SMTP email notification system
 for efficient communication.

DocumentGuard | Blockchain-Based Document Storage System

August 2022-December 2022

- Developed a secure, decentralized document storage system using Blockchain, **IPFS**, and **AES** encryption, reducing document tampering risks by 40% and enhancing data accessibility by 35%.
- Implemented **SHA-256** hashing and a peer-to-peer network with Socket Programming, improving data retrieval speed by 25% and ensuring document integrity across distributed nodes.